Guide to the John James Audubon Print Collection [1820]-1860, 1985 PR 162
New-York Historical Society
John James Audubon print collection
[1820]-1860, 1985 (bulk 1832-1845)
New-York Historical Society
PR 162
1.88 Linear Feet (2 boxes, 1 drawer)
The Audubon print collection contains hand-colored aquatints, lithographs, chromolithographs, and items of ephemera of or pertaining to the work of John James Audubon, including both original prints from his famous color-plate books of natural history, and later, derivative prints of the same.
Provenance
The collection is mainly comprised of gifts from a variety of donors. The proof prints were purchased in 1947.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to thirty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. See guidelines in Print Room for details.
Biographical Note
Scope and Content Note
The John James Audubon Print Collection spans the period from ca. 1827-1860, and 1977 to 1986 and contains both original prints from Audubon's famous color-plate books of natural history, and later derivatives. The collection is divided into three series: Birds of America;Viviparous Quadrupeds of North America; and Miscellaneous.
Arrangement
The collection is divided into three series.
Missing Title
Series I. Birds of America
Series II. Viviparous Quadrupeds of North America
Series III. Miscellaneous
Related Material at the New-York Historical Society
Portraits of John James Audubon and his family can be found in the Portrait File (PR 052). The Department of Prints, Photographs, and Architectural Collections also holds a double Elephant folio set of Audubon's Birds of America, and the N-YHS Library has an Octavo set of the same. The Manuscripts Department holds some of Audubon's correspondence. The N-YHS Museum holds Audubon's original watercolors for Birds of America, as well as other work by Audubon, including an empty marbleized paper and leather portfolio, of double Elephant folio size, with "Birds of America" printed on the cover, which was used by Audubon himself to carry his watercolors or sample prints as samples to show to potential subscribers.
Visiting cards; Proofs; Lithographs; Ephemera; Chromolithographs; Circulars; Aquatints; Prints -- Coloring; Natural history -- United States -- Pictorial works; Birds -- United States -- Pictorial works; Audubon, John James, 1785-1851. Birds of America; Audubon, John James, 1785-1851. Viviparous quadrupeds of North America; Childs & Inman; Havell, Robert, 1793-1878
- Series I: Birds of America, 42012
  Scope and Contents note
  Series I. Birds of America contains material related to the original double Elephant folio publication of Birds of America, published in numbers from 1827 to 1838. Plates for this edition were aquatinted by Robert Havell, Jr., after drawings by Audubon, and were hand-colored both by Havell's studio staff and Audubon's wife and children. This series is arranged into three subseries: Pattern Proof Prints, Loose Plates, and Facsimiles and Reproductions.
  The fifteen color proof prints were used as patterns for the colorists of the aquatints. These sheets give primary and detailed evidence about the coloring process; several have penciled color notations, and one has a notation for textual change. Eleven loose plates from the double Elephant Folio edition, all marked with Havell's name, are also included. One of these, the White-headed Eagle, appears in both uncolored and colored format. Several modern reprints of Audubon's birds can also be found in this series.
  Prints are arranged by plate number, where known.
  - Pattern Proof Prints, 42029
    - Common Yellow Throat [Plate 24], 1827-1838; 42044 (Box 1, Folder unknown container)
    - Kentucky Warbler [Plate 38], 1827-1838; 42043 (Box 1, Folder unknown container)
    - Chestnut Sided Warbler [Plate 59], 1827-1838; 42042 (Box 1, Folder unknown container)
    - Autumnal Warbler [Plate 88], 1827-1838; 42041 (Box 1, Folder unknown container)
    - Carolina Titmouse [Plate 160], 1827-1838; 42040 (Box 1, Folder unknown container)
    - Orange Crowned Warbler [Plate 178], 1827-1838; 42039 (Box 1, Folder unknown container)
    - Tree Sparrow [Plate 188], 1827-1838; 42038 (Box 1, Folder unknown container)
    - Manx Shearwater [Plate 295], 1827-1838; 42037 (Box 1, Folder unknown container)
    - Yellow Breasted Rail [Plate 329], 1827-1838; 42036 (Box 1, Folder unknown container)
    - American Widgeon [Plate 345], 1827-1838; 42035 (Box 1, Folder unknown container)
    - Rocky Mountain Plover [Plate 350], 1827-1838; 42034 (Box 1, Folder unknown container)
    - Lapland Longspur [Plate 365], 1827-1838; 42033 (Box 1, Folder unknown container)
    - Golden Winged Warbler [Plate 414], 1827-1838; 42032 (Box 1, Folder unknown container)
    - Tawny Thrush/Townsend's Thrush & Canada Jay [Plate 419], 1827-1838; 42031 (Box 1, Folder unknown container)
    - Western Duck [Plate 429], 1827-1838; 42030 (Box 1, Folder unknown container)
  - Loose Plates, 42020
    These prints are housed flat in a map case.
    - White-headed Eagle [Plate 31], 1828; 42028 (Box Unknown container 689 for instance of White-headed Eagle [Plate 31], Folder 1)
    - House Wren [Plate 83], undated; 42027 (Box Unknown container 690 for instance of House Wren [Plate 83], Folder 1)
    - Connecticut Warbler [Plate 138], 1832; 42026 (Box Unknown container 691 for instance of Connecticut Warbler [Plate 138], Folder 1)
    - Sooty Tern [Plate 235], 1834; 42025 (Box Unknown container 692 for instance of Sooty Tern [Plate 235], Folder 1)
    - Great Marbled Godwit [Plate 238], 1835; 42024 (Box Unknown container 693 for instance of Great Marbled Godwit [Plate 238], Folder 1)
    - Red-necked Grebe [Plate 298], 1836 (Folder 1)
    - Tell-tale Godwit or Snipe [Plate 308], 1836; 42023 (Box Unknown container 694 for instance of Tell-tale Godwit or Snipe [Plate 308], Folder 1)
    - Redheaded Duck [Plate 322], 1836; 42022 (Box Unknown container 695 for instance of Redheaded Duck [Plate 322], Folder 1)
    - Trumpeter Swan [Plate 376], 1837; 42021 (Box Unknown container 696 for instance of Trumpeter Swan [Plate 376], Folder 1)
  - Facsimiles and Reproductions, 42013
    - Great Egret, 1977; 42019 (Box Unknown container 697 for instance of Great Egret, Folder 2)
      General note
      Printed by the National Audubon Society
    - Canvas Backed Duck, undated; 42018 (Box Unknown container 698 for instance of Canvas Backed Duck, Folder 2)
      Printed by R. R. Donnelley & Sons, courtesy of the Field Museum of Natural History
    - American White Pelican, 1985; 42017 (Box Unknown container 699 for instance of American White Pelican, Folder 2)
      No. 152 of 500, printed by Princeton Audubon, Ltd
    - Wild Turkey, 1985; 42016 (Box Unknown container 700 for instance of Wild Turkey, Folder 2)
      No. 135 of 500, printed by Princeton Audubon, Ltd
    - Purple Heron, 1985; 42015 (Box Unknown container 701 for instance of Purple Heron, Folder 2)
      No. 140 of 1500, printed by Princeton Audubon, Ltd
    - Brown Pelican, 1985; 42014 (Box Unknown container 702 for instance of Brown Pelican, Folder 2)
      No. 1136 of 1500, printed by Princeton Audubon, Ltd
- Series II: Viviparous Quadrupeds of North America, 42005
  Series II. Viviparous Quadrupeds of North America was issued from 1845 to 1848. Six loose plates of small animals from that book are held here. All are hand colored lithographs by J. T. Bowen after drawings by John James Audubon.
  - Common American Wildcat [Plate 1], 1842; 42011 (Box Unknown container 703 for instance of Common American Wildcat [Plate 1], Folder 3)
  - Cat Squirrel [Plate 17], 1843; 42010 (Box Unknown container 704 for instance of Cat Squirrel [Plate 17], Folder 3)
  - Red-tailed Squirrel [Plate 55], 1844; 42009 (Box Unknown container 705 for instance of Red-tailed Squirrel [Plate 55], Folder 3)
  - Brindled Weasel [Plate 60], 1845; 42008 (Box Unknown container 706 for instance of Brindled Weasel [Plate 60], Folder 3)
  - Brewer's Shrew Mole [Plate 74], 1845; 42007 (Box Unknown container 707 for instance of Brewer's Shrew Mole [Plate 74], Folder 3)
  - Carolina Shrew [Plate 75], 1845; 42006 (Box Unknown container 708 for instance of Carolina Shrew [Plate 75], Folder 3)
- Series III: Miscellaneous, 41999
  Series III contains nineteenth century material that does not readily fit into the above two series. A lithograph of a "Marsh Hen," by the firm Childs and Inman of Philadelphia and published in 1832, is one of a very few known copies of this print; the only one of Audubon's birds to be separately printed in this format. Little documentary evidence exists of Audubon's foray into lithography, but the print is thought to have been drawn on stone by Albert Newsam in the summer of 1832.
  Included in this series are four of John James Audubon's calling cards; all but one note his distinction as a "Fellow of the Royal Linnean Societies of London." A prospectus dated June 1834 announces the forthcoming publication of the double Elephant folio of Birds of America, and seeks subscribers. The series also includes a title page from and another prospectus for the 1860 double Elephant size reissue of Birds of America, with chromolithography by J. Bien, which was published by Roe, Lockwood, and Son, of New York.
  - Marsh Hen [no plate marking], 1832; 42004 (Box Unknown container 709 for instance of Marsh Hen [no plate marking], Folder 4)
    Lithograph, drawn and printed by Childs and Inman, Philadelphia
  - Title Page from Birds of America, edition of 1860, published in New York by Roe, Lockwood & Son, New York, chromolithography by J. Bien, 42003 (Folder 5)
  - John James Audubon, four calling cards, three as "Fellow of the Royal Linnean Societies of London", [1820-1839]; 42002 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Brochure advertising double Elephant Folio edition of Audubon's Birds of America, 1834; 42001 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Brochure advertising double Elephant Folio and Octavo chromolithography editions of Audubon's Birds of America and Viviparous Quadrupeds, as well as a stand on which to display the book. Published by George Lockwood, 812 Broadway, New York., [1860]; 42000 (Box 2, Folder 8)